[Music]
the stoa
is a digital campfire where we cohere in
dialogue
about what matters most at the knife's
edge of what's happening now
[Music]
all right hey guys how you doing
um welcome to the second session
of the 21st century version of wisdom
with greg
henriquez did i get it making him
um this is the second of four sessions
uh last week with greg we talked about
um the theory of knowledge system the
first part of kind of how
from the big bang to today could you try
again
uh it looks like peter siri wants to
take over again
i was on mute so that wasn't me this
time
getting more sophisticated so um
today today greg greg is going to
present about justification systems
um the format if possible could be the
same as last time where it's about
45 minutes 50 minutes of lecture and
then questions
and what can really help me out with
questions is if
you write q um and then write out your
question and then if you see a question
you like two plus one if you see a plus
one do it plus two
so you can just stop talking
so if i if i see a plus two or plus
three it's a lot easier to find one of
the top voted questions
if you don't want it to this is all
going to be recorded put on youtube so
if you don't wanna be on youtube
just let me know say hey please read
this out for me
and i'm excited uh today's session is
going to be a lot of fun
so greg take it away all right
great well first off peter thanks so
much for having me here
i really enjoyed it last time peter's
coming down to
tok society on monday we're looking
forward to that
um actually i should say if anybody's
interested in my
uh work in society i do have a theory of
knowledge society
um we have a pretty active listserv and
anyone can just contact me email me
and i'll be happy to talk with you about
that and put you on that if you have an
interest
um so yes uh thank you anjin also thank
you peter because you've now hooked me
up with anjen
and anje and i've been hanging uh and
connected it's been great
uh so and also others i look forward to
talking to several of you contact me
after this so
it's been great so last time i sort of
went through the garden
uh and then we touched on that and then
we went to the tree of knowledge
uh frame of reference uh which is the
first
branch on that theory of knowledge tree
behind me
uh and today what we're gonna do is
we're going to then take a tour of the
second branch
called justification systems theory um
i'm going to share my screen here in a
second
uh then next week just so for folks
we're going to talk the problem of
psychology and the need for a new
metapsychology
and then the last week we'll do
metapsych tech
or some version of that meaning sort of
what kind of metapsychological
coherence frame of mind do we need for
the ecology of practices
what work have i done in that and then
how can we cut together
so anyway i'm going to go ahead and dive
into this
lecture part and then we'll have half of
it for
questions so let me share
my screen and we'll get to it
okay okay
so um today we're touring the branch two
second branch and in fact uh where it
all started actually
in 1996. and uh on anjin's prompting i'm
going to tell you a little bit about
that
he thought that was helpful to frame but
what is this thing justification systems
theory
it's a theory of human
self-consciousness and the evolution
of the culture person plane of existence
i'll talk a little bit about what
exactly you mean by that but if you
recall from the tree of knowledge
matter life mind and culture represent
different planes of existence in the
in that language system
so now let me tell you a little bit
about
uh just justification systems theory so
the first thing i want to do
is just let's orient to this thing
because the uh the argument is this is
pretty much where
ever you look uh that human beings are
very much like
fish and water uh that the person
culture plane of existence
uh is everywhere around us and we see
through it but we don't always see
uh it uh as much so
so uh let me tell a little story so it's
i'm deep in the struggling with the
problem of psychology
uh i've learned a lot about evolutionary
psychology
i've learned a lot about cognitive
psychotherapy and psychology that's what
i'm doing my dissertation on
psychotherapy psychodynamics around
psychotherapy i'm learning
and it's daunting on me that a key issue
which you'll see a little bit elaborate
on
here is as the evolution of language
takes off
we're then forced to give accounts we're
forced to justify our actions
and then we really become the justifying
ape
um and the argument is that we basically
are oriented generally to justify our
actions in accordance with social
influence
um meaning sort of the ways in which
we're positioned in the social world so
we're not inclined to give explanations
or accounts
that really diminish us now it isn't
now it's certainly the case that many
people sometimes do seem to give
accounts of themselves that seem to
diminish them
and i actually was substituting for i
was working in a neuropsych rehab
uh when this idea really popped i mean i
had been playing around with those with
this
um and then i had to fill in somebody
went on vacation it was over the holiday
and i was then in the psychiatric domain
and then i did a eval and a woman who
came in and just made a suicide attempt
and she her father had died six months
earlier i don't remember exactly the
cause
she was about late 20s mid-30s
she lived by herself in borderline
poverty
very much isolated her narrative
is a narrative you see in the clinical
world fairly regularly unfortunately
she lived in rural vermont we grew up in
rural vermont um and her father was a
raging alcoholic
who dominated his submissive timid
mother
um and she had an older brother
now one of the striking things about
this woman was how
she totally saw herself as inadequate
ineffective really
hated herself uh and basically and
although
for example her iq of memory serves was
somewhere in the 110 ballpark she
thought ourselves as stupid
i think objectively most people are
founders relatively attractive she saw
herself as ugly
essentially she was downgrading herself
on every indicator now
if you are oriented to justify yourself
in a particular way
why on earth would somebody down rate
themselves
and yet we do see it in a subset of
population subset of people
well here's the dynamic that where the
exception proves the rule so
um when she was growing up her older
brother is four or five years older
started becoming defiant of her
alcoholic father uh
and as an adolescent he started to rebel
and they got into physical fights and he
would be physically beaten
uh by his father and she remembered a
specific incident
uh where he was her father was beating
her uh brother
um and he was he said to her he said why
can't you be more like your obedient
sister
and that's stuck in her head she told me
that story okay
well as she relayed the story and i was
thinking my frame was oh my gosh our
self-concept pertains to the way we
justify ourselves on the social stage
the social influence dynamics something
really clicked where the exception
proves the rule here
think about it so she's eight her father
experiences defiant from a 12 year old
boy who's going to be a lot stronger
than she is and he kicks the boy's ass
what's going to happen if she asserts
that she's a valuable person that she's
smart that she
warrants power that he's treating her
unfairly what happens is that
well very likely uh the calculus would
be you're going to get
you're going to be beaten you're going
to have your physical safety put an
obvious risk so what happens then is if
you turn against the self and you say
i'm actually not worthy
what that justifies then is submission
indeference
uh it's basically a white flag and if
you look at the animal kingdom you see
white flags all the time
okay and so here we had a self-concept
system that turned against itself but if
we understood the adaptive history
we see that submission and deference was
essentially demanded by her
authoritarian abusive father
and all of a sudden the exception plays
the rule
now the narrative i tell on this one is
that i this clicks on me and i'm
up and uh you know am i really excited
and i start chatting with my fellow
uh doctoral students i was a doctoral
student in the university of vermont at
the time
uh and i'm explaining oh my gosh this
idea
of justification i now can figure out at
least with this case how the exception
proves the rule
and maybe we really are justifying and i
can start to see this in my clients and
you know and it turns out that i look up
the clock and it's 6
20. now my wife was waiting for me and
this is of course before the days of
cell phones the mid-1990s here
um and i'm like oh god i'm supposed to
be home at six all right
so i said all right i gotta go head out
into my car get in my car
we only live about five minutes away we
live in a little town called
winooski which is near burlington i get
in my car two seconds after i get out
all of a sudden they're doing road work
and what should have taken me to five
minutes to get home takes me 15 minutes
to get home so i walk in that door at 6
35 and i've been late
earlier a week earlier and you know you
don't want to wait to keep your spouse
half an hour waiting so she's sitting
there pissed um
and it's like where you been and without
two seconds worth of thought i look and
say it's the traffic
that's right they're doing can you
believe it they're doing traffic okay
uh and that's that's why i'm late all
right i didn't have to think about that
they didn't take any delay there it is
okay now if we then back up and we look
at actually what happened
20 minutes of the reason i was late was
because i was paid attention myself
obsessed with my theory wanted to be
discussing that okay 10 minutes was
because i was traffic
right it was because of the traffic it
didn't take my mind
any effort to pull out the traffic
reason and hand me
uh hand us that that wasn't
self-conscious it was an
automatic another story i tell about
this is when i was watching my
uh in a different context watching my
four-year-old daughter and two-year-old
son
and they were playing initially and then
they got into it a bit and i was just
watching them
my son hit my daughter a little bit and
then she pushed him down
knocked him down okay he starts crying i
assure my machine and said hey
what happened here my four-year-old
looks at me and he fell
okay notice it explains why he's on the
ground and crying but it subtracts some
key elements of the information
the autumn a justification filter all of
a sudden you're given accounts
okay so if we situate ourselves in this
what you see here
is what i'm going to invite you to think
that justification dynamics
in the way in which we explain ourselves
are absolutely ubiquitous
i mean also i find a lot of mileage when
i'm doing clinical work
uh as we start to get into people i
invite them to think about their
justification
narrative they're telling me an event
about what happened or who they are
what they get into it i'll often reflect
sounds like your justification narrative
is this
in fact narrative psychology and
psychotherapy is a big deal i add the
word justification
because you can then once you do that
you see the structural and functional
organization you see that actually
you're trying to legitimize what is an
art
in relation i'm going to be arguing is
the essence of
persons behaving in culture
there's a psychologist by the name of
peter osario who argues that the
definition of a person
which actually is different than a human
being a definition of a person
is an entity that can self-consciously
justify themselves on the social stage
and take account and responsibility
for why they do what they do
and finally we're going to talk about it
also as this network of propositional
knowing
a network of propositional knowing so
this is a ubiquitous concept
and when you learn to see the world
through the lens of justification you
see it everywhere
like right here like i am justifying to
you that justification systems theory
is a good way to think about the world
okay so to now position ourselves i'm
going to locate just
in the context of the unified theory
where since we're all fans of john
verveigh or at least i
project that out into the world uh we're
going to make connection to his work and
a theory of propositional knowing
we're then going to go back in time and
identify the problem of justification
how it would have emerged in the course
of the evolution of language and then
how that sets up
a thing called the updated tripartite
model which is a model
of human consciousness and then finally
we'll talk briefly about the culture
person plane of existence and we'll
allude uh to the brilliant work of peter
lindberg and talk to about culture war
2.0
and the current state of our
justification systems
and their fragmented pluralism as we go
through this time between worlds
okay so we want to locate this thing in
this overarching
system so the unified theory of
knowledge tree identifies eight key
ideas
around knowledge justification
investment influence adaptation
development well-being and mindfulness
this course fundamentally wisdom so now
let's locate it in this particular
domain we have
last time we covered the tree of
knowledge system
which orients us to the first branch and
justification systems theory is the
joint point
between mind and culture on the tree and
it sets the stage then to give us
a updated tripartite model of human
consciousness
and the evolution of the culture person
plane of existence
in fact that's what this step picks
right here is the joint point between
mind and culture on the tok
a theory of culture that includes the
evolution
of human knowing including science that
actually becomes a big deal later on
not necessarily in this talk but in
other contexts it offers what's called a
reverse
engineering hypothesis about the
evolution of human reason giving
and the evolution of our propositional
knowledge system
um and then we can let's move into the
domains of human consciousness that this
maps
okay so uh i'm going to argue that it
offers us a useful way to understand
human consciousness we can now get
situated
so if we take our take a second here um
i'm going to identify three broad
domains one is the experiential self
this also another word for this is
phenomenology this is the thing that
goes offline when you fall asleep and
when you come online it integrates your
senses and gives you your point of view
in the world your first person
perspective behind your eyes between
your ears
that no one else can get direct access
to and have a private self
that's a narrator and a public self
which you can then report on
i'm going to introduce another
vocabulary that will to overlap some
with this
and that is there's a thing called mind
1a
okay this is this is a model of
consciousness and i want to
differentiate it from a model of
neurocognition although these two
domains need to be
uh to make the clear some of you may
know of steven pinker's work
this was an influential book in my day
1997 i think it was published
stephen pinker articulates how the mind
works
this is a theory stephen picker's work
is a theory of what i would call mind 1a
in other words in fact he says it's not
a theory of sentience
and it's not a good theory of
self-consciousness either it's a
neuro-computational functional analysis
okay of a bit from an evolutionary
perspective
about how the nervous system as an
information processing system computes
uh behavior over behavior in my language
is called mind1b
because it's mediated through
neuromuscular it can be seen from the
outside
but relevant for us are the two other
domains of mind one of which is mind two
so when i use the word line two and some
other settings or if i use the
experiential sentence mine two refers to
phenomenology
first person experience of being then we
have mind three
a the interior narrative and mind three
be the exterior narrative
uh the reason i believe that this is
really crucial is because and according
from my vantage point
we're enormously confused in our
understanding of how to talk about the
mind in general its relationship to
consciousness
its relationship to self-consciousness
in fact as i will talk about next time
the problem of psychology is very much
the fact that we lack a conceptual
grammar that allows us to effectively
talk about mind and behavior
and what the mind123 map does is it
tells you actually how to sort out
that and give rise to a much more
clarifying
vocabulary for our purposes
justification systems theory is about
mind three it's emergence it's storm
it's structure
so uh let's just touch briefly on john
vervicky's four
ps of cognition uh there's john talking
about them and
on rebel wisdom and lost ways of knowing
also includes greg thomas it's a great
half hour presentation there and john's
four piece of knowing
start with procedural knowing this is
the most basic forms of knowing
um it connects insakes now certainly you
can get very very complicated forms of
procedural knowing
but most obviously our procedural
knowing that's then dropped into our
habits becomes surely automatic
and is generally the least conscious
forms uh that john
talks about perspectival knowing refers
to point of view integration
senses into a perceptual whole it's
connected to this screen
the global neuronal workspace of
subjective experience if you want to
throw a bernie bars reference in there
john also talks about participatory
knowing
which really is when you start to engage
your perspective in
regards to the whole animal arena
environment and then you're engaged in a
particular kind of novel
task that isn't reducible to procedures
that you already learned but are new
so when you're first driving you're
engaged in a lot of participatory
driving and then you can reduce a lot of
that for procedural knowledge
okay and then finally there's
propositional knowing which is
language based knowledge reasoning and
reason giving
i often point out that us as human
beings are both
primates and we are persons
um and we can very much align these
three domains of knowing the first three
p's with our primate
in other words we share uh procedural
perspectival and participated norm with
the primate kingdom in fact we share it
with lots of the animal kingdom
yet the advanced symbolics and tactical
propositional knowing well
that's uh what makes us human beings
quite unique uh because it enables us to
become fully functioning
persons so
um justification systems theory provides
an evolutionary framework for them
for propositional knowing and then how
it shapes
um human self-consciousness and culture
it enables us to understand a reverse
engineering lock and key formulation
that gives rise to this map updated
tripartite model
and helps explains the processes that
give rise to the evolution of culture
across the last several tens of
thousands of years
it is something to that needs to be
explained because if we look at the
archaeological record we see over the
last 50
75 to 50 000 years uh basically a human
mind
big bang uh where we see the evolution
of culture
transforming how humans interact with
the environment uh of course the
archaeological record is
is the technological material culture of
things that are left behind
but there's a huge amount of evidence
that suggests that this thing has
exploded over the last 50 000 years
just posits that humans have a elaborate
self-consciousness system because the
evolution of
language creates a thing called the
problem of justification and i want to
highlight
exactly what that is but the bottom line
answer is because of language humans
become the only animal that has to
explain
why it does what it does um first there
are actions and motives and feelings
and then with language self-conscious
reasoning must emerge
i also want to be very clear here that
the rest of the animal kingdom is very
rich
in both its mental life and its
communication capacities
but there's a big difference between
communicating
why you have to do what you did or why
you did what you did
as opposed to engaging in all sorts of
other kinds of communications
um just hang out with your dog sometime
and try to get it
to give you a reason why it did what it
did you can hang out with your dog in an
unbelievably rich participatory way uh
but getting
your dog to explain why it did what it
did um is a totally different problem
in fact uh my friend joe mikulski had an
opportunity to have lunch
uh or a special dinner can't remember
exactly with jane goodall uh and he's
very familiar with this he asked her you
know
do chimps as far as you're aware ever
justify their actions
uh and your answer was a reality no they
have very very
many advanced mental abilities but no
they don't necessarily do that
um so there are three basic postulates
to this
justification systems theory uh the
first is the evolution of propositional
language must have created the adaptive
problem of justification
which and i won't get into it too much
actually breaks down into three
different related problems one of which
is the analytic problem
another is the personal problem and the
third is the social problem of
justification
that is the adaptive dynamic problem the
consequence is the human
self-consciousness system
functions as a justification and that
gives rise to specifiable dynamic
relations with the subjective self and i
should say here the interpersonal world
that means this is the design features
that then match to the adaptive problem
and you will see this with the shape and
structure and domains and functional
relations
that we see with consciousness
finally just provides a frame for
understanding the rapid evolution of
human culture over the past year and the
nature structure function of the culture
person plane of existence that's the
three postulates they weave together
so postulate one human language resulted
in the emergence of the adaptive problem
so we can start here with wherever
language emerges
and we can argue that initially what you
get is you get you have shared
intentionality cooperation around big
difficult
items certainly for a long period of
time humans are engaged in intense
social cooperation this is long before
um symbolic language at least and
certainly in this model would have taken
off
uh and you can have gesturing you can
have memetic communication meaning we'll
match each other we'll have
all sorts of different kind of shared
attention and then what will happen then
is that shared attentional space then
gives rise for the symbolic
tagging uh symbolic tagging which will
then capture various objects various
activities
uh you say things like antelope there or
kill
uh these will capture various elements
however
okay this although this is important
this is not exactly the tipping point
uh that leads to the big bang from this
uh perspective in transition
what happens is when the development of
arrangement of a symbolic syntactical
structure that leads to propositions
such as
there is the mammoth let's start the
hunt notice these are propositional
claims
all of a sudden a propositional claim
activates a totally another
kind of response that says why should we
we might get killed okay when we say
just kill that's not to say that they
would
there would be no way to negotiate a
kill but you cannot negotiate whether a
command to kill
with the dynamic of justification
without a propositional set of claims
once you have propositional claims then
all of a sudden you get what's called
question answer dynamics and dialogues
okay why because a propositional claim
sets the stage for a truth claim that's
what the depth propositional is
in definition which then in turn gives
rise to the potential for a counter
factual
i.e maybe that's wrong okay
and now what that does is that then
allows for the cognitive
gadget of a question that then poses the
opportunity that maybe the negative
a guy by the name of rory bashkar often
expands his critical realism into
dialectical critical realism
because he expands from oh this is what
is wait a minute what is the negative
space we always need to create negative
space contingency considerations
well actually a proposition sets the
stage for negative space contingency
and we see that all the time in the
capacity for questions questions then
raise why what where how
what do you mean you now get to fill in
or question
or challenge it's the question answer
dynamics that fundamentally in this
remodel
is the tipping feedback group that sets
the stage for general justification
and this gives rise to the problem of
justification in general which is
determining what is and what the group
ought to do
and this sets the stage for general
reasoning in the social context
okay and ultimately this is going to
create a feedback loop where individuals
are engaged in the process
of the construction of systems of
justification
okay so reason giving tied to outcomes
gives rise to traditional practices
and indeed the argument here is that
these systems of justification
in the last 40 30 20 000 years
then set the stage for animistic belief
value systems
oral narrative traditions okay that then
set the stage for individual wise elders
who can understand the narrative history
of their particular tribe across the
generations
and bring explicating
sense-making systems so that you can
then interpret
debates interpret the nature of the
animistic gods and spirits
one's place in nature how to negotiate
between various conflicts
uh and we ultimately then see uh the
first deep
cultural meaning making systems in the
oral indigenous tradition
and this is what is meant by cap culture
with a capital c
in the tree of knowledge and unified
theory
a recent book by hugo mercer and dan
sperber
delineates how dialogue gave rise to
argumentation and justification
in fact they come up with a strikingly
parallel theory
the one i developed uh 15 years prior to
its publication
so now i want to but the justification
hypothe
hypothesis into systems theory goes much
further than just the idea that
the problem of argumentation and
dialogue
um i'm a clinician and so i'm
deeply focused on the process by which
people narrate to themselves and others
and how that relates to various elements
of their psyche
okay and how it would relate to how they
might construct a narrative of self
and where for example the shadow comes
from why do people have such radically
different
approaches and narratives like if you
talk to a husband and wife in conflict
why do they have such unbelievably
different versions of reality
uh why do if you watch a football game
on one side you think the refs are
unbelievably
lame against you and then the other side
also thinks the rush lame only on the
exact opposite way cheating your team
why are people like that what is the
filter well it has a lot to do
with the problem of the personal into
social dynamics of justification
so here we have an imaginary situation
where alpha male
who comes around and noticed is that
somebody's hanging around with his
parabond insignificant
other and so we can imagine that beta is
attracted to alpha's mate
and alpha wants to know why he's
spending time with her
why are you hanging around with my pair
bonded up
okay now this creates a very
tricky dynamic okay and by the way this
is going to now
set up all right one of our big
dynamics of what we need to learn at the
culture persian plane
which is how do you give an account for
your behavior we go back to my
four-year-old daughter her initial
account of why her
two-year-old brother was sitting on the
ground crying was he fat
okay but then i say well actually it's
more complicated than that right
so now somebody else can give a frame of
reference in relationship to that based
on evidence and then hold you
accountable
so how do you tell the story of who you
are and what is real
in an analytic sense but at the same
time manage all the complicated social
dynamics
so this problem of justification then
sets the stage
so that according to it language is a
window into the mind
as such while there's much that we want
to share freely
when our interests don't align like with
alpha and beta
okay what we do and how we share our
thoughts is crucial and it's tied to an
absolutely essential resource
social influence this is the capacity to
move other people in accordance with our
interests
all right if this is true then the
social self-consciousness system
should have been shaped to construct
information about the self and the world
in a way that solves the problem of
personal social
if so we should see evidence for this
okay
so this gets us to the second postulate
that the shape
design functionality of the
self-consciousness system
should be operating as a mental organism
of justification that navigates the
social influence dynamics
and it's going to bring us to the
central insights
of this guy you probably know
okay now let's return to alpha and beta
okay and we are now faced with this
question of now all of a sudden having
to be given an account
and let's imagine beta says hey
i hope to separate the two of you and
take her as my mini
after all this is an accurate
translation of his underlying drive and
desire
now let's think about that for a second
and think about the problem of social
influence
can we imagine that this might be a
problem if he accounted for his behavior
this way
well so apparently obvious to us this is
the lens that we see through
what i would like to pose to you is that
you are constantly
and exquisitely attuned to your reason
giving and the social influence and when
we see somebody say something like this
you say well is that guy got a problem
not to be pejorative but immediately if
somebody would make these kinds of
comments from a clinical perspective i'd
be like oh does this person have a
little bit of autism
okay autism has actually got some mind
blindness at least according to simon
baron cohen which means it's very hard
to detect the social dynamics that are
associated with it so you know are not
attuned to these kinds of things
and you find yourself saying
unbelievably blunt things that sound
tone deaf and get you in trouble okay so
what does he generally say
he oh she's hey man no problem she's
teaching me to plant seeds
okay now what is this this could be a
lie
but i'm going to propose that it's
something not so much a lie
here okay we're going to come back to
this but we also now just immediately
need to say well
if we are in this kind of situation now
alpha's got to decide
whether or not this justification is
legitimate or whether it hides something
and he's bs'ing
all of a sudden now we're going to get
into the problem of bs which is
unbelievably central
to social world um and complication i
know john talks a lot about
but the idea here is that we're not just
talking about the evolution of lion and
deceit although
obviously the distinction between
private thought and public thought
brings to rise that filter in filtering
dynamics between them but i'm more
after the subtle dynamic okay which is
this is how do we fundamentally frame
ourselves
and the argument here is before he is
ever in question beta must deal with the
possibility of being questioned
that as we walk around with the idea
that we're about ready to be given an
account
in fact i deal with people all the time
in the clinic room are hyper
self-conscious
essentially chronically imagining
account giving where they might be
punished or criticized and then trying
to preempt that
with narrative about why they're okay or
why they better not act in a way that it
affords that so the argument is not that
he's prepping a lie
the argument is that he's finding a path
of narrative of activity of other things
that allow him to create a narrative
that's consistent in accordance with
social influence
and although his underlying desire may
well be to get close to verse that
ultimately has an opportunity for that
kind of connection
the i am trying to have her as a mate is
repressed
outside of awareness okay
in other words the dangerous impulses
now
are taken outside of what's socially
acceptable and put into the shadow
side of the subconscious portion of the
psyche and as soon as we say that
we're like oh my gosh where are we now
we're on freud's tripartite model
so freud of course fundamental
observation over the years once he first
discovers the unconscious
and then develops a model for the
various domains
of structural function relations in uh
in the three persona of the id the
underlying animalistic impulse that
wants something
for its own pleasure versus the
ego which is then going to operate on a
reality-based principle across time
and then in conflict with an
internalized standard from what's the
socially acceptable rationale from the
idealized parent
that then tells you what you need to do
in order to get what
social acceptance in a societal frame
that has certain values and rules
okay so the super ego then is that
internalized
punish yourself first so that you
internalize the standards
so fundamentally we're talking about an
analystic self-centered urge
and an internalized standard that a
self-consciousness system now needs to
regulate in reality
so here's the model also this time it
also has the topographical features
and relationship to the structural
features in regards to it
so what we're going to now see is that
the updated tripartite model has lots of
dead
indebtedness to freud but it also
updates it in relationship to modern
science and clarifies the topographical
and structural functional dynamic
relations it places them
on an evolutionary foundation and it's
going to make them consistent with
social cognitive psychology
and was going to make it consistent with
sociocultural principles
so the domains are the experiential
system the private self-consciousness
system and the public self-consciousness
system
it's also then corresponds to mind 2
mind 3a and mind 3b
the mind two nonverbal is the perceptual
emotional core of the self it's the
first person view on the world
okay these are your perceptions your
basic drives motives emotionally
organized pleasure and pain we can
dialogue a lot about
the layering in fact this is what i'm
doing a lot with john verbaki and
untangling the world not
is delineating the perspectival and
participatory aspects of mind two
how it emerges out of mind one meaning
the neurocognitive functionalist
processes that then become
conscious what are the elements the
metaphysical elements
and the functional elements and the
evolutionary elements of that
um we should note that for freud when
freud used the term consciousness that's
why i meant to
say that in the topographical element
when freud used the word consciousness
he actually means what i mean by
self-conscious
okay that is the explicit reason giving
understanding
so when if something is not explicitly
reasoning
so freud does not differentiate between
perspectival perceptual consciousness
and self-conscious narration he just
uses his own consciousness which by the
way is why that topographical model is
not ideal
um i'm happy to take questions we can
talk about what's called the
experiential self
um how this connects into what's called
episodic memory
um and how the self then extends through
time uh how
animals as you get more and more
sophisticated you will develop an
intuitive
implicit experience of self one's
perspective animals will demonstrate
even things like ravens will demonstrate
that they have access to particular
that they know things that the other
individuals don't know it's really
really
interesting so i can talk about the
development of the experiential self
which is different a little bit than the
experiential screen of consciousness
although they are definitely connected
we can certainly state that the
experience of red is fundamentally
different than
the thought and reflective narration
about what redness is
and this gives a surprise to the private
self-consciousness system
which is the seat of our self-reflective
awareness our narrative scream of
conscious justification
are it then stores our explicit semi uh
net uh our semantic knowledge of self as
well as then that will tie in with our
episodic memories to give rise to
narrative of self
our sense of self concept our ideology
morality and worldview what we believe
to be true about the world
and is often we're interpreted as ego
interpreter narrator i'll use the term
interpreter sometimes that's a nod
to michael gazzaniga and the work he did
with sprit brain
which is of unbelievable demonstration
that if you isolate the left hemisphere
from knowledge
of what's going on stay in the right
hemisphere it will simply convalbalate
socially acceptable rationale for why
you're doing what you're doing
in a direct alignment with
justification systems theory but the
idea of thinking
something is quite different uh than the
idea of saying something
so we might come across this individual
with some funky sweater on
and we might think to ourselves hey i
don't like that shirt
it doesn't look good on her but if you
say that publicly
that comes with a wide variety of
different implications
okay um and we engage all the time with
public private filtering i'll give you
another little anecdote i'm on many many
different listservs
about four years ago i was on a listserv
i was in sort of a dispute with a guy i
felt was really obnoxious
and some of my friend back channel and
said hey what's that guy's problem
and i said oh this guy's got problems
he's kind of really annoying he always
does this
hit send and guess what i had replied to
the entire list
of 250 people all right and immediately
i noted out a jolt of pain and reached
toward the computer as if i could pull
that sent email back out from the ether
okay
why what happened there is well
privately i could say one thing about
this guy i didn't want to say it to 250
people
that's a private public filtration
so what do we normally say when we come
across these things we white lie
and say it looks nice why because in
terms of social influence dynamics
okay this is a lot easier
so the public self-consciousness system
is what we publicly share and proclaim
ourselves to be
it's our persona the image we try to
project largely defined by audience
you know note i'm a guy that emphasizes
integrity i'm a guy that emphasizes
consistency but believe me if i'm
talking to person a
and they're having a conflict with
person b i'm narrating with person a
and boom i'm totally different in many
ways than i'm talking with person b
i mean what i emphasize what's justified
what i think about
all of that stuff is framed by who it is
that the audience is
pay attention to yourself you'll see
that okay
it's operating always when we lie
deceive or manipulate others from true
intent
okay and it's going to relate deeply to
our felt sense of our place in the
relational matrix
okay so now there are these three
domains experiential
well private and public that's really
important to delineate but even more
important to get theoretically
sophisticated around is to identify the
dynamic and
relation okay the first is the potential
filter this is between mind one the sub
non unconscious domain of neural
information processing and then how does
it become
we could talk about exactly that again
that's a john verbake and i
primary problem so how does the
intentional filter actually bring give
rise to something in
that's consciously experienced at the
perspectival level
there's the experiential and to freudian
filter
this refers to the dynamic attention as
you start to become aware of it how do
you narrate it
and then how does your top-down
intentional shift begin to shift
based on what you want to pay attention
to what you don't
and then finally the private to public
hey do i want to tell this person how do
i want to come across what do people
think
am i going to be an impastor whereby my
persona really is what what other people
see and it hides my true self
these are all dynamic relational
interfaces between these different
domains of the human consciousness
system
so that attentional filter depends on
what we become aware of both in
perceptual awareness
and depending on how we narrate it
there'll be an iterative feedback loop
that freudian filter fundamentally
involves the way we keep the private
self works to keep stuff on the off the
stage of consciousness
i like to tell a story one of my friends
when we were growing up of course
when i was hanging out and most of us
were heterosexual when we were 15 16 oh
my gosh look at all the hot girls
he was always lukewarm okay in
relationship to this and then in
college uh ultimately he comes out of
the closet
okay so what do we mean by that it means
when he was 14
15 he wasn't having the same feelings he
was basically playing along
back in the 80s being gay was a little
bit different than me and today we were
more judgmental less enlightened during
those times his father was a bit
homophobic
so he kept himself in the closet it
means that underlying his experiential
self
as that started to come onto the stage
his homosexual desires
the justification and public image stuff
was so powerful it would
cut it off he would shift he would
repress those desires
until finally he got to a place where it
was obvious enough and safe enough and a
long standing enough so he first came
out to himself that's through the
freudian filter
into the private narrator and then
ultimately came out to others
ultimately coming out of the closet is
through the private self and into the
public
okay um so all of this then relates to
freud's fundamental observation that
there's a fundamental tension
between that ego self-conscious system
uh what is expected of itself and the
underlying drives images and impulses
okay and then we have what we show and
hide to others
it's called the reverie because the
difference between one social self and
authentic self is emphasized by rogers
when someone really hears you without
passing judgment on you without trying
to take responsibility for you without
trying to mold you it feels damn good
this is
actually when you're seen known and
valued through and through and you don't
have to filter and justify
when you're held and yes if you're gay
we still love you or whatever it
is that you then feel reflected back
into your organization process and your
value for that i've talked about that
known in value through and through
that's an unbelievably nurturing thing
in the humanists capture
okay and finally just provides a way to
understand the evolution of human
culture in the person culture plane of
existence
that's this on the trade of knowledge
we can jump right up here and basically
like well wait a minute okay what do we
mean by that well
if we take peter lindberg's argument
around what are these memetic tribes and
why all of a sudden what's happening
i would argue what's happening is the
paradigmatic frame of justification
that was operating in modernity is
breaking down
our sense-making narrating authority
structures
are no longer able to hold together uh
with clarity
to socialize us so that we all have some
shared sense of identity in fact
everything is losing its authority the
post-modern critique the craziness of
the digital
the craziness of the wars create created
massive flux in our paradigmatic
understanding
and so what's happening is a breakdown
in that and then all these different
tribes these paradigms of justification
um what they do in this article which is
so excellent is they then
it comes with a whole deconstruction of
what 25
or 32 little tribes with their core
justification they have their iconic
person their core principles
and then they define themselves against
what are they fundamentally against
so you then have what is and what ought
to be who do you want to follow what's
the social influence who are the threats
how are we trying to gain influence and
what's the fundamental narrative so it's
an
excellent delineation of cultural
paradigms which really are systems of
justification you can see that by
how they define what is and ought to be
and how they get then defined against
other systems which define what isn't
ought to be and it allows us to see at
the macro cultural level we're in
a serious flux right now because we
don't have good systems of justification
actually help us
make sense engaging sense making why all
of a sudden are these emerging cultures
asking the question how actually do
do we make sense how do we gain a system
of justification we can communicate
and have some degree of coherence
civilians can hear and whatnot
and finally i'll end with some sort of
notion about where we are in the
evolution of cultural justification
i'm going to argue and have suggested
this that initially what you get is oral
indigenous justification as narrative
and hunter-gatherer dunbar tribe
you get individuals embedded in nature
seeing animist experience
face to face across a long period of
time that's actually what we're prepared
for
and as long as we work together you
actually be known in value to that kind
of
scenario and i believe the oral
indigenous context is really
is going to be much better for our soul
in many ways we then get civilized at
about 10 000 years ago and certainly by
5 000 years ago we see writing
massive civilizations you cannot engage
in oral indigenous you have much more
formal systems for a whole host of
different reasons so you get formal
priest formal uh
argument you get writing you get more
much more complex and abstract analytic
things you need
laws and national identities and clear
hierarchies
that legitimize a particular national
religious philosophical
way of being so now you have a much more
abstract uh
formal system of justification we see
500 years ago we get the emergence of
modern science
and then the sort of global at least
coming off the west sort of this global
capitalistic scientific way of thinking
in the last 50 years we see a
post-modern critique
okay and i think this is a very nice
shorthand
lean rachel anderson does a wonderful
job of framing the kind of sensibility
that we need here
one that recognizes each of these four
and then cultivates one that includes
and transcends
to create a cultural consciousness that
actually embraces the essence of the
best of an oral indigenous
what is a formal civilized legal
pre-modern identity what's modern
science what's the post-modern critique
of that
and can we cultivate a system of
justification that's the meta-modern
identity accordingly rachel anderson
and i agree very much with it so
ultimately
a theory of propositional knowing it
identifies three key domains
experiential private public
in relationship to the updated tritar
type model and these are connected by
three filters
and it sets the stage the evolution of
culture and the nature of the persian
culture person plane of existence and in
particular where are we
what kind of justification system
attitude do we need in the 21st century
if we are actually going to cultivate
a vision of wisdom thank you
quite the whirlwind um
thanks greg um
i wanna i wanna just kind of see if i'm
understanding how to place this
and if i'm understanding kind of the you
know explain it like i'm five version of
it
um last week you you talked about
like the relationship between all these
different domains
you can actually understand them um
in a united way and that helps you see
that a human
could be understood at the matter level
at the life level there's evolutionary
forces at the mind level
you know the different behavioral
aspects of what it means to be human
it's a lot easier to eat doritos when
it's on your
countertop versus if it's in your
cupboard
and then if i'm understanding this
correctly it's
the next level the culture you're making
the argument that that leap from mind to
culture
it was language but specifically
propositional
forms of justification um
that defined that leap and since we're
so much a cultural creature today
you can most understand the basis for
the way we think about stuff
by understanding this justification
hypothesis
that's a yeah that's a very good way of
saying it let me be
uh sometimes language is is easy to get
confused around because there's lots of
different meanings
uh it's capital c culture person okay i
wanna
i wanna yoke that stuff together and be
clear and the reason is
people will often point out and say wait
a minute animals have culture
okay um and they'll point out that
different animals engage in different
practices
you know macaque monkeys will wash
potatoes to learn how to wash potatoes
they'll
transfer those practices um there's a
wonderful book by carl safina called
beyond words i wish it was called before
words but nonetheless
it tracks the very different cultures of
things like elephants
uh that the killer whales wolves okay
so let me first say that little sea
culture or the shared set of
sort of communal values and practices
you can see these in other higher
animals very clearly
okay and and if you mean by culture just
the shared sense of community and
practice
and that gives a unique flavor to
something that does have an
intergenerational learning tradition
then i want to be clear that that's an
over generalized meaning of the word
human culture and the culture person
plane of existence is
absolutely transformed and defined by
this thing we call language
in particular propositional language and
the networks of propositions
that then yoked together to create these
systems of justification
so that's a very important difference
and so little sea culture at the animal
level does exist
but then you get into big capital c
culture and the nature of persons
no other animal other than a human being
is a person from this perspective
um and and then that is the problem of
then full explicit intersubjective
self-consciousness
uh then the idea of what is justifiably
good and then
how do you solve it and bad and then how
do you count yourself
yes that's absolutely key and then that
lens allows us to see
the way in which we are both persons as
we operate in culture and also our
primates
because we do all the other things
primaries do like eat doritos
sleep and have sex
is the implication from this then kind
of like in economics we
model oh people are these rational
beings and anybody in the world is like
no we're not we're all
crazy and irrational and we rationalize
things and have all these beliefs
it so kind of is the takeaway or
implication from this that like the best
way to understand a human
is not this rational reasoning being but
it is
consciousness and that reasoning evolved
um for justification like that's why
going to somebody and
explaining 50 facts about climate change
doesn't necessarily change their mind
could you like help sure sure so uh
um a couple of things there so first let
me say that the
word we we split off analytic truth
and this is one of the problems of
philosophy they split off analytic truth
claims
two plus two equals four okay a priori
truth games these are absolute
then there's this rationalization
dynamic where people to hide
underlying reasons
and they lie and they do all that stuff
that's what social people do
what we're really after is analytic
truth claims
okay nice thing about the word
justification is it actually shows
that as a dimension okay so einstein
comes up with e equals m c squared in my
system that's an analytic justification
okay if he was late to his wife coming
home and said hey
you know the traffic well that's also a
justification it's a rationalization
okay justification then gives you the
lens to see the dimension
uh all the way from analytic claims okay
to uh hey let's go to the movies claim
uh to a defensive claim to a lie in fact
i did the context of justification
anywhere from a con game
uh to a defense attorney uh and
courtroom to the courtyard
uh to the lab all right so the first
thing i would say is yeah
be aware that we actually now with this
concept we actually now
create the dimension okay of
propositional knowing
and philosophy tends to and we get
taught oh well there's truth claims and
then there's
it's like well actually this is the
first thing you want to do is create
this category
and then you want to divide it up
secondarily okay
so then the other thing is absolutely
you will both want to see the ways in
which
we are unbelievably shaped okay anybody
that
that speaks to the socialization of
knowledge
of our development uh if you develop if
you adopt a social constructionist view
of the importance of knowledge you will
then say oh my god it's unbelievably
important that i was
born into you know i was born in north
uh
north america northern virginia i have
two white parents who are highly
educated well that tells a lot
about me if i were born 30 000 years ago
okay or even 30 years ago in saudi
arabia
the cultural systems of justification
and my whole sense-making system would
be radically different
so the power of these narratives
historical context and shaping what we
do and what we believe and why we do
them
is enormous at the same time we're all
primates
okay so then this gets into what is it
about our human nature
uh certainly one of my big struggles
actually this is an intersection where
i'm learning what's the evolution of
human nature
relative to the power of cultural
construction
and the answer is well it depends on
what lens you look at it from one level
it's like
it's not that powerful at all we're
primates we're going to reach for the
doritos 90
you can nudge people in certain ways
yeah they rationalize but that's all
post hoc
it's all brain-based here and now you
know reward dopamine
the whole context is context of
justification the reason you're doing
the lab is actually because the way you
justified
so believe me it's unbelievably
important the question is how
okay so what is the intersection between
the cultural con
constructive systems and the uh up uh
upload of nature and that intersection
this provides that
frame of mind so
i'm i'm curious um
i'm curious in in some like ways day to
day or week to week
this might like this this framework
helps you understand stuff
yeah what you see on tv or seeing people
argue about something in a shopping mall
like could you share some examples
of of course yeah i mean first off
that's how i see
verbal comment uh you know i i started
much
like mercer and sperber okay so
um it's so deep in me that it's been so
transformative
when i was when i initially landed on
this i was then going to do i was
trained as an experimental
social cognitive psychologist and i was
then going to do research
i was starting to do the process of like
okay what are the predictions that it
makes so i can take this into the lab
and see if this thing actually works
okay
well as i started to do that guess what
i realized i was doing was realized i
was building a justification system that
then tested and blah blah
okay and ultimately what then happens is
although you can certainly do that it
does make very clear predictions i think
the predictions are unbelievably
and there's a lot of interesting things
to engage in
but ultimately what happens is it
becomes a description
okay it becomes a description of what
you are doing and as you are engaged in
uh so just watch all right so now just i
can't watch like a political debate
right obviously i'm sure all of you have
this problem okay but basically what are
you doing
you are essentially defending your team
that's the whole
damn goal all right so you're completely
motivated to defend your team
and do whatever you can to justify
social influence for your team
that's why you never answer the question
and in truth you're just the
old content of time
and now we've hired people that all they
do is defend the team
rather than actually engaged in the
analytic problems that we have so it's
all social personal that's why i have to
turn off the debates i can't even take
it anymore
because they're so obviou if you have my
lens it's so
obvious that you're just a corrupted
human being all you are is just a
narrating bullshitter across some other
predetermined motive
if you want to be that way fine but
that's not the way to be
okay at least as far as my value system
so ultimately it does so it says the
whole part there's
it opens up a whole set of well yeah why
am i given the reasons that i'm giving
all right and and what it tells you is
actually yeah you think that you're
doing it but actually by design there's
a little set point that says develop
socially acceptable rules based on your
calculation
and start generating narrative all right
and quite frankly
what you'll find is just people are
engaged in mindless bs justification all
the damn time
and that's painful and you'll find
yourself doing it i often refer i used
to refer to myself
as a verbal okay and then encourage
other people
and and so what it does it does it will
be humbling a bit
okay because once you actually see it if
you're not practice when you first see
it you're like
when i came in and realized oh my god
the traffic was immediately basically a
reflex of justification that i engaged
in and then i saw myself doing it all
the time
it's a little humbling
so yep it's everywhere like i just
justified by you we can
engage in justification analyses
um i'm going to ask one more question
and then i'm going to switch to that
are um are there synonyms here to
justification like it's storytelling or
beliefs like
could you help us with the like why the
word justification and maybe how is it
different than
these other things we'll say ah a human
is a storytelling person a human's uh
yeah um
well just you know that's a good that's
a good question uh
i guess what i would say is it's just
the nexus point of so many different
things
it's it sort of is like i fell into it
and it does this it does this it does
this
the issue is that it's the intersection
of proposition and legitimizing
it's propositional legitimizing so what
it does is it connects
the language system okay and it's medium
and then it connects it to is ought to
do
in influence and investment so just
it makes it alive so proposition so and
it is that intersection
and then you can use that intersection
uh you know
with practice again this is unbelievably
in my i mean this is i mean
i landed on this idea i said law it took
decades for me to flush it out
so really don't try to grocket all them
all at once
okay the issue basically is plant the
seed of justification
you know and then just start using it
it's like well what is it and where and
how how do i apply that
okay and now it's like oh okay there's
analytic justification where i'm
actually asking truth based claims
there's social and personal dynamics
well it's a private narrator personal
oh okay so there's a social dynamic what
did i find myself wanting to say this
well there's a social personal dynamic
if we're all getting together in a group
now we have to decide hey are we going
to meet what's the identity of us oh
that's a social dynamic
is there a truth claim that's on the
table that's an analytic
dynamic and then you start getting into
that
and the whole thing is like an onion and
it layers itself so
what i'll say is let it grow don't try
to reduce it and just
just be with it and you'll see it will
just morph
and move but it doesn't lose its
coherence it actually just grows
in it at least that's my experience
could could you give me an and explain
it like i'm five version of what you
just said i don't think i quite
understood
and then yeah that wasn't a
five-year-old version um
i so
okay so a couple of i'll i'll do it this
way
so your propositional system is trying
to get a handle on it right now
okay all right so that's that's a good
thing to
note all right so there's a
propositional sense making system trying
to get a handle on
and it's sort of it's sort of both so
broad that it gets slippery it's like
where's the tree where's the forest
okay so then we could just say oh that's
what your propositional system is doing
all right so the other thing that i'll
say is most of the time
your propositional system is just
tracking systems of justification
all right so mostly assuming so in
everyday conversation
hey can hey dear can you go get me that
glass of milk i forgot it
oh notice i said i forgot it which was
implied
but it then says actually i'm taking
responsibility i said i forgot
okay and now why am i saying i forgot
well because i'm actually
asking you to spend money if i just said
hey go get the milk
guess what what she would have said
you if i'm talking about my wife
okay he's like what the hell you go get
the goddamn milk right but if i say i
forgot it
then what does that do it basically says
i'll to acknowledge that
that i was foolish i should have been
writing it there you'll see all the time
that you'll give disclaimers
okay as you give accounts you're like
well hey this may come across as a
little insensitive
trigger warning okay what's that well
that's a disclaimer gives me safe space
so i can then say something that could
potentially be offensive
well that's creates a justification
dynamic
so anyway the point of visit london is
actually it's very it's a somewhat
difficult question to answer
because of its its ubiquity and depth
so sort of like yup it's basically let
yourself
don't try to reduce it to a thing just
let yourself recognize that
it's an ocean
so it's like question answer dynamics
are what get you into this and then it's
trying to fit in
socially but then also at the level of
truth and so on that then is how this
carries itself out is that yeah yeah
that's good i mean so then
so i i built the whole unified theory of
knowledge around it
okay so that because it opened up so
many damn questions that i then had to
resolve
all right that's another way so i you
know if i had an endless number of
sense making things like one of the
things we're not talking about at all is
the influence matrix
all right in fact i just got off the
phone with jordan hall because i was
like
jordan when you get into you and daniel
schmuckenberger getting into the concept
of influence
be very aware that that's a very
complicated concept you have to
deconstruct
okay like for example there's power
influence there's love influence there's
freedom dynamic around influence most
importance is the distinction between
relational value and influence
and social influence at a pragmatic
level especially if you start to get
into game b dynamics because game a is
all about instrumental social influence
and really there's core relational value
dynamics about aligning those
i know i'm not maybe making a lot of
sense here but the bottom line is is
that
yeah there's a it's a massive amount of
layering
okay and then you have to get into the
layering well that's the social dynamics
what are the personal versus
social dynamics and then what's the
socio-historical dynamics and so forth
okay so and in fact the entire unified
theory is essentially
an encapsulation around once i opened up
the
unlock the key of justification and then
was like boom you know it's like
it's everywhere
wow you see the water yeah all of a
sudden i saw the water
right and it was very deep and very
broad and it took me lots of different
places
like a damn garden
let's let's go to some of the questions
that are in the chat
i'm going to start with fred and after
that um andy so fred if you want to ask
your question
you're muted fred
um
it looks like
oh okay i'm here thank you
yes uh
[Music]
well um i'm just fine about my question
again first of all greg thanks for
taking time to
explain your theory and all the
epiphanies that
led you to it and engines uh
you saw the water the fish saw the water
and i certainly don't claim to
understand the breadth of
what you're presenting um
[Music]
but a couple of questions about um well
first of all are you curious if you have
a theory of positive psychology or human
flourishing
um
that's that's good nothing um
i'm sorry did you you asked what about
positive psychology in florida
do you have it does your theory do you
have a theory of positive psychology or
human flourishing
yes i mean the uh the seventh branch
on the tree back there that's uh the
nested model of well-being
um in fact i critique positive
psychology because
uh they are basically um
unfortunately they follow mainstream
academic psychology uh which is
basically an empirical discipline
um and as such they basically
empirically carve up
uh virtue in the positive domains which
is very
useful uh but they if you just carve up
empirical constructs uh you basically
have what's called the sandcastle
problem meaning
they're going to build lots of different
super cool um idiographic
or research driven concepts like oh
growth mindset
or oh character virtue or all these
kinds of notions or subjective
well-being
um the question is though how do they
interrelate what values do we
how do we put this together how do we
put it together with the dark side
of human experience and a holistic view
so i'm a really big fan that
you know clinical and empirical
psychology move from the dark side into
the positive that's good
unfortunately martin seligman's version
of positive psychology
um is in my opinion a decent start
but unbelievably shallow and not very
philosophically sophisticated
so what so what do you need to add back
in
i i mean i'm with you people who do
psychotherapy with uh for folks who are
unhappy trauma survivors
etc is unbelievably important
um but i would say that our psychology
looks like it's missing all these other
dimensions it has no normative aspect
uh in the way clinical psychology is
practiced
so you're so what are the dimensions
that you feel need to be added to
seligmans say or
barbara fredrickson or pick them yeah
yeah no it's not so much a dimension
it's really the way in which they are
put together so you create a whole
understanding so if you take is um you
know
the question fundamentally then is like
like so seligman tries to get to this he
gets to what's called perma
okay and which is basically sort of a
domain of sort of
positive emotion uh he gets into
relationships he gets into achievement
uh i can't remember all the anyway perm
is an acronym for the big domains that
he identifies
so if you fill these in then you have
some more you diamond
which is an aristotelian notion of sort
of the ultimate good life
so i am what you see happens in positive
psychology
is that the field splits between the
empiricists that do subjective
well-being
at least at the well-being level versus
the more functionalists that do
um or and and philosophically
sophisticated they do
aristotelian optimal functioning um so
one of the things that you would then
one of the things that the reason i
built the nested model is to
understand how to put together the
empirical
frames of reference with the more
value-laden
optimal functional frames of reference
into a holistic model of what
well-being is that's coherent and
appreciates both the science side
and the value-laden side okay so
actually it turns out to be pretty
simple
at one level in the sense that actually
the proper model of well-being according
to this is that it starts with a
first-person experience
uh uses the empirical analysis the
subjective well-being
for positive affective negative affect
uh
general narrative which is general life
satisfaction specific domain narrative
which is are you happy with your
relationships happy with your job happy
with finances
then you drop that into a psychological
functioning
and organismic functioning physiology
that's what a medical doctor would do
then you place that individual in both
the material and social environment
and you see harmony to the extent that
there's harmony and to the extent or
their suffering gives you
an illness health dimension but
ultimately you have to then encapsulate
that
in the ideology and values of the
evaluator
okay you have to recognize that actually
if you're going to make a claim about
well-being
all right you have to so for example if
i
identify somebody let's say oh they're
really healthy physically
they're climbing up in their job they're
happy with their family they're doing
what they can
and i tell you oh by the way it's 1942
and they're leading auschwitz
okay if i tell you that as opposed to
some other individual then
most people say i don't know the
well-being of the auschwitz leader
bugs me a little bit and the reason is
because ultimately when we start to
think about well-being
it's a value-laden constant so we
actually want to tie it back to our
ethical
values and worldview so so anyway
positive psychology is super important
but like the rest of psychology it's a
fragmented nightmare
at the level of its coherence uh and it
needs to be woven together
so once we can then have a coherent
model then we can actually generate
and provide people the wisdom that it
affords but in a
frame of understanding that they can
actually have rather than the fragmented
particulate frame
that actually both exists and then it's
translated by
great answer thank you
thanks for the questions great
andy and then after that roy greg i
love justification systems theory to
explain
the concept of the closet trump voter
so there's clearly a non-coherence
between the
public self the private self and the
justification that goes on when
you publicly say or say to yourself that
morally abhorrent or whatever i hate the
guy and yet you vote for him
question is what has changed besides
proliferation of media in the last
50 years that makes in your opinion
um justification systems
different now than 50 years ago
great question that's a wonderful
question i think it
warrants a lot of study um here's my
basic
answer um is that you're basically
getting the crest
of modernity in the 1960s okay
and what i mean by the crest of
modernity i mean that you come off a
world war
two um you you then especially like in
the united states you then get an
establishment
of the institutions the understanding
the roles and functions of what
individuals are doing and essentially
the knowledge systems are
adequate to give people a sense of
security clarity and understanding
okay um so in other words basically it's
up to the task
now what you start to see in the 1960s
is uh you know
there has been these horrible world war
one world war ii
and and these deviations and we have
these serious concerns and with nazis
and we see oh my god
um there is some profound problem with
modernity
and white male domination and and
colonialism and so you see
social justice movements you see
starting to critique
a philosophical continental philosopher
the the depth and truth claims
transcendental truth claims
but really in the 1960s and 70s all
there was a lot of social unrest
obviously 68
things like that but ultimately people
are like oh yeah we
we have enough sense making relative to
the information ecology relative to the
change relative to what's happening to
be good enough we feel like we're on
progress
and we're actually sane and okay we
trust the broadcasting functions and the
structures seem to be so we have faith
in the institutions
okay and then basically
the world is hap is changing so fast at
the level of technology
at the level of polluting the
information ecology digital tips
okay we connect we hook ourselves up
into an enormous number of different
things
and then we start facing more and more
challenging so
the size of the actual complexity of the
information ecology the rapidity of
change that's happening
the availability of different
communication networks okay
essentially in a period of couple
decades completely outstrips the old
paradigms capacity for
regulation sense-making and control okay
so that by overall then now the rules of
the game
and i this is the shorthand for this is
digital okay
from the vantage point of the tree of
knowledge when you get the emergence
of a novel information process and
communication system
okay like gene cells okay genes
processing for store information the
cell computes information and then
engages in communication with other
cells
the nervous system processes information
animals communicate
and then people talk process symbolic
information
communicate well cells are totally
different than chemistry
animals are totally different than
plants people are totally different than
animals
each one of those is a totally different
dimension of complexity
as a function of information processing
communication
so when i found the tree of knowledge i
knew the 21st century was going to be a
show
okay about six months after i discovered
six weeks because i knew
that we had laid down the internet we'd
lay
developed artificial intelligence we
were building a communication system
that is going to open up a set of
possibilities that it was just not going
to be able to be contained in the old
institutional system
and that's the short answer is that i
think that we have access to information
perspective and and ways of being that
our knowledge systems are not
they're not good justification systems
for it and they're not up to the task
these are the things that ground our
institutions so everybody's losing trust
in the institutions everyone's looking
around going there's something deeply
wrong
and unsustainable about the structure
because the change factor
is grossly outstripping the constraint
capacity
during all sorts of chaos hopefully that
chaos will be realized into opportunity
we'll find new equilibriating i talk
about the fifth joint point
new equilibriating structures that then
allow us to get settled
and then you know find a way to the 21st
century is a lot saner than the current
state of affairs
so it was less complex 50 years ago to
form heuristics um
how how were tribes formed differently
how
uh you know let's say uh if you were
protestant reformation time and
you um
didn't want to believe the the only
hierarchy the catholic church or
something
there was less complexity with knowledge
but it was so monopolized
that weren't you still afraid then to
um yeah of course but the broadcasting
function of the church is just so
strong it can stay for 500 years you
know right because in other words
in other words that so you're a closet
atheist right and you might
look of course you might loathe it you
hate the freedom listen i'm glad i don't
live in the
hung in about about five seconds right
um
in relationship to the time right
there's no there's no opportunity
the system the church controls the
justification and
institutional infrastructure so
unbelievably tightly
and the information capacities is so
unbelievably limited
that it can just regulate so that if it
then has a spies out everywhere and if
you start doing heresy like atheism
um we're going to find you and we're
going to root you out and of course
there's a subset of jews that they have
to hang around and lend money
you know but basically the entire
infrastructure of the
of the polis the government everybody
is online with a particular system of
justification
so so it has massive control and the
information technologies that are
available
most people can't even read okay so it's
only narrative so how how do you get
your message out
how would you know right um if if
three set three uh village is over
there's another atheist
right okay you said would never know but
now
obviously on the internet uh you know
you all you need to do is just to do a
google search and i can instantaneously
out of seven billion people or however
many people are actually on the internet
i can instantaneously do a search and
find
people that have fetishes for
high-heeled shoes or whatever it would
be
right um so the information uh ecology
and the availability of lines of
communication
uh the internet i mean writing changed
it dramatically
okay telephone changed it uh all of
those media marsha mcluhan's a great
theorist he talks about how the
mediums shape us and totally change the
patterns of behavioral investment
now that we have well the argument is
that digital is changing us like
no no other system it's even makes
writing look like a little drop in the
bucket
so digital completely transforms the
information network
and then that opens up all sorts of
adjacent possibilities the structure is
not built for
and now everyone's sort of what has
legitimacy what can we trust
is this actually going to hold together
how has the
um positive side of this structure
[Music]
influenced things that one would
consider now to be
second order uh game b um
so let's use two examples um 10 years
ago 15 years ago
smoking in restaurants had no momentum
to be banned
legalizing pot gay marriage right
why did these things change so quickly
over the course of a 10-year time period
and how does that differ and relate to
media compared to 50 years ago yeah
so it's great um well first off what
you've seen
uh is that over the last 50 years you're
the you've seen the building of the
postmodern critique
okay and the post-modern sensibility
which is challenging
traditionalist authority okay in certain
regards
all right so you have that that
mentality
is gaining wave so that the millennials
are not looking at their elders going
gosh you guys knew everything man thanks
so much
it's like no you guys are totally
clueless okay uh and they have a totally
different frame of reference for justice
for what's value for what's appropriate
and they're not shy about it
all right um so and that that wave of
challenging the authority of tradition
has been building okay and part of it is
made accessible
and in many ways a good way i mean the
old white male tradition
believe me i thank god that's coming
down and we're opening up all sorts of
different lines of diversity people can
be much freer to be themselves
the opportunities are unbelievably
tremendous uh and i'm
and you know there's a lot of truth to
see pinker's enlightenment now
in relationship to the general
trajectory of reason and humanism
uh giving people more and more
opportunities i think there's a lot of
downsides to and i think the trajectory
is bad
unless we change our fundamental
understanding of human nature
we're on a dangerous path i believe like
schmucktenberger and
hall talk about this is self-terminating
if we don't change the fundamental
structure
so but but what i've been amazed at
connecting with all the seers is the
number of people are seeing this
same sub mountain from different
perspectives and the emergence of things
like peter
lindberg and the steward of the show and
bringing people together
to think differently and realize to get
outside the box
um now i'm a traditional academic i've
been inside the academy my whole life i
came from
you know two parents who are professors
and then into a professorship
but why am i here because the damn
academy is
just it is stuck in its old modes of
being i get super frustrated i'm like
listen people
wake up it's time for an upgrade in your
operating system you guys are
trapped in the past 50 years ago was
like 500 years ago now
and we all need to be waking up because
the entire educational system the entire
knowledge system
and you know most of my colleagues are
well i've got to get this randomized
controlled trial paper out and it showed
a little bit of difference and i hope it
will get through peer review
that is so done that's like sorry
that is not gonna cut the mustard we're
talking about a fundamental shift at
least that's where i am
and rob scott i know would appreciate
that comment a fundamental shift in our
identities
is what i believe we need to engage in
so
that's my thank you
um we got about six minutes left roy do
you think
um you wanna ask your question and maybe
on two minutes just to close up
thank you uh greg for your talk
i'm a slow talker so i find uh
fasttalker
floods me quite easily so i'm
hoping you can keep it
uh fairly simple for uh for me
i'll try to speed up my question
no worries i've been in the construction
industry
i i noticed an erosion of trust in that
for four decades six years ago i began
the transition to alternative dispute
resolution
and i now do act as a neutral
on construction disputes okay
so the acronym adr
i hadn't even heard of until i made that
transition
i get a lot of value out of um
the psychology and
meeting crisis information i'm hoping
you could
give me a good reference for further
research that would integrate
your world with my world of uh dispute
resolution in construction
um sure with that first off thanks
thanks for that roy i appreciate
that i'm a clinician
and so i've done a lot of marriage
therapy and of course work with people
managing being stuck in conflict with
themselves
with their past with their future with
their wives
so it's definitely close to my heart
and finding pathways of effective
remediation and mediation
are absolutely central to
some of the work um i'll
point you to my homepage unified theory
of knowledge
uh and it's got eight key ideas on it
um when when people are asking me
you know kind of well how do i apply
your system
in a way that helps me especially when
people are in conflict
um the the thing that i try to help
folks do uh or that what i offer them
is a frame for an integrative approach
to psychological mindfulness
psychological mindfulness is the process
by which we
enter into our space and allow ourselves
to become aware
and attune to what is happening as
opposed to mindlessness
right which is when we're just defensive
and reacting
so we want when we're dealing with
individuals that are actually at least
open then to the process by which they
would then
find a more adaptive resolution if
they're in conflict
we try to add us what's called the stage
of change level we want to get them
contemplating about ways in which they
would be different
okay um and then
invite them to uh be open to the
possibility
of that difference um and then if you if
you get that and you get some commitment
to that then the question is
how how how would you then cultivate
that attitude
and generally what you want to try to do
is you want to foster levels of
awareness acceptance and then
change in various parties okay and
realize the difference between
sort of ego commitments to maladaptive
patterns uh
versus openness to potential adaptive
valued pathways
how do you do that well the shorthand of
what i offer is one thing called
calm okay which is which is an acronym
first it's like hey let's get calm let's
recognize that when we get pissed off
we drop into defensive mindsets it's
either attack we freeze or flight
or we fawn and apologize and then we
present it later these are
classic stances in common and we want to
basically we want to acknowledge those
and we understand where they come from
our body and our emotion
we also realize that they're actually
short-term emotional responses that are
very valuable and oriented us but rarely
valuable in the impulses that they
orient us towards
okay at least in the short term so we
then want to listen to them and listen
to their appraisal listen to your heart
and then open up an attitude both
intra-psychically
and interpersonally that fosters
curiosity
okay so curiosity yes i see somebody
talking about restorative justice here
that's beautiful too
um that's a nice helpful uh way of
thinking about
different there are lots of different
ways to peace and and connection but
anyway
curiosity first orients individuals to a
more mindful state that then
adopts a position where you can be
wondering about oneself and one's other
where does this come from what's really
going on what is the what's the salient
issue and what's the deeper issues
perhaps then there's issues of
acceptance
this is a capacity to recognize that
actually yeah life sucks sometimes you
get hurt
how can you sit with what is with
distress tolerance with clarity
okay then l stands for loving compassion
that's an attitude of just basic dignity
towards others and that you hope
that they aren't suffering this is again
identity to itself another
and then m refers to
a motivated toward valued states of
being in the short and long term
so if i'm in negotiation what is the uh
what is the moment what do i hope in
relationship to the end of this
negotiation
and what is my long-term view ultimately
all the way up to what might be called
eulogy
values which is what kind of person do i
want to be and what kind of ancestor do
i want to be
so that then places it on the context of
time
so what that basically is is that tries
to create the kind of arena
that enables individuals to be able to
come together who have been wounded
who've been traumatized or bitter with
each other who have real disputes
but at least it soothes and orients
towards
adaptive outcomes and it identifies the
underlying emotional triggers
and how to hold them how to honor them
but also not how
uh to be held a hijacked limbic hijack
people say about your relationship
greg it's 3 30 now would you have any
time afterwards
um if we were to end this session just
to hang out with a couple of us there's
yeah sure if uh i'm i'm totally open to
that
okay so yep i i i've got certainly until
four so people want to hang
i don't know if we do we need to get off
the stella um
so um
so let's just quickly formally close um
so the recording can be done i to plug
an event there's an event later today
at 8pm eastern by justin weinberg
it's called disagreeing well
and the summary is well disagreement is
often treated as a problem weinberg
thinks there's some
overlooked upsides to it you'll talk
about the value of disagreement
obstacles to disagreeing well and how we
might better get along with those whom
we disagree
so pretty good to show up on the same
day as
greg's justification systems amen
um greg any closing thoughts and any
kind of
foreshadowing for what next week is
um you know i guess the closing thought
is just
learning how to observe your
justification systems realizing that
they're not reality
they are very important aspect of who we
are uh but being able to shift
your perspective on them see them in
other people
recognize the dynamics that's a i
believe that's a very valuable thing so
that's what i'm happy to share
um and next week um is there a theme to
the session
yeah so next week we will kind of come
in with a slightly different angle we'll
talk about the problem of psychology
uh we'll need to understand what that is
from my vantage point
uh then what we'll do is we get to open
up and do a conversation with a special
guest
uh zack stein uh who talked about his
own metapsychology
and then we'll have some iterative
dialogue between his version and
experience of the field of psychology
why it led him to his view uh what my
view is and
you know how to see them complementary
somebody asked questions about how those
two things were late i can't remember
who
but somebody did and it led to a lot of
good discussion
that's going to be really exciting um
all right thanks everyone thanks greg
have a great day and